Guide to the Thomas Mayer Papers, 1950s-2014 RL.11374
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas Mayer papers
1950s-2010s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mayer, Thomas, 1927-2015
RL.11374
2.0 Linear Feet
Thomas Mayer was an American economist (1927-2015) known for his work in economic methodology and monetary policy. His papers include published works and drafts of his writings and research and a small amount of correspondence between him and other economists. A portion of this collection is born-digital material, which is not yet available for research.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Mayer (January 18, 1927 – June 12, 2015) was an American economist who was professor of economics at the University of California, Davis. He previously taught at West Virginia University, the University of Notre Dame, Michigan State University, and the University of California, Berkeley.
He is known for his work in monetary policy and economic methodology. Mayer received his Ph.D. from Columbia University in 1953.
Access Restrictions
Collection papers are open for research. Collection's original born-digital and electronic records are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of use copies.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Thomas Mayer Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016.
Collection Overview
The papers held in this collection consist largely of Mayer's writings, in both final and draft form, which span his professional career from the 1950s until the 2010s. There is a small amount of printed correspondence, including notable economists Milton Friedman, Roger Backhouse, and others. The bulk of the collection consists of born-digital materials, which contain both electronic drafts and email correspondence. As of January 2017, this material is not yet available for research. Contact Research Services with questions about accessing that portion of the collection.
Monetary policy -- United States; Banks and banking -- United States; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Economists -- United States; Economics -- Methodology; Economics -- History; Friedman, Milton, 1912-2006; University of California, Davis. Department of Economics
- Writings, 1953-2013 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  A portion of Mayer's many articles and published works are represented in this series, which include both final versions (some photocopies, some offprints) as well as drafts and research for various articles. Subjects include monetary policy, bank regulation, ethics, methodology, and other topics in economics. Materials are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Banking Systems, 1982 (Box 1)
    Encyclopedia entry
  - China's Financial Reform and Monetary Policy: Issues and Strategies, 1996 Dec. (Box 1)
    Published by The 1990 Institute
  - El debate de la politica monetarista: Una retrospectiva informal, 2003 (Box 1)
    Published by CLM Economia
  - A Defense of Limited Interventionism, 1962 (Box 1)
    Draft
  - In Defense of Inconsistency, undated (Box 1)
    Typescript
  - Disclosing Monetary Policy, 1987 (Box 1)
    Photocopy of Monograph Series in Finance and Economics
  - Dishonesty in Economics, undated (2010?) (Box 1)
  - The Distributional Effects of Interest Rate Ceilings on Time and Savings Deposits, 1982 Aug. (Box 1)
    Working paper
  - Do Changes in Asset Prices Denote Changes in Wealth?, 2000 and undated (Box 1)
    Drafts
  - The Failure of the New Economics, 1959 (Box 1)
    Offprint
  - "A Fairy Tale" by Anon Ymous, undated (Box 1)
  - The Great Depression and History Textbooks, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Honesty and Integrity in Econometrics, 2012 and undated (Box 1)
  - How Fast Does Inflation Adjust to its Underlying Determinants?, 1981 (Box 1)
    Published by Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco
  - Ideology, Objectivity, and Fairness, undated (Box 1)
    Drafts and research
  - Impact of Budget Proposals on Income Maintenance Programs, 1985 Feb. 14 (Box 1)
    Statement by Mayer during Hearings before the Committee on the Budget, U.S. House of Representatives
  - Inconsistency and Slippery Slopes: In Defense of Whimpery, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Inflation Article (Chinese translation), 1994 (Box 1)
    Published in Management World
  - The Influence of Friedman's Methodological Essay, 2004 and undated (Box 1)
  - Input Lead Times for Capital Coefficients, 1953 Dec. 22 (Box 1)
    U.S. Bureau of Mines, Office of Chief Economist
  - Interest Rate Deregulation and Monetary Policy, undated (Box 1)
    Comments by Mayer at Asilomar Conference
  - A Justification of Inconsistency, undated (Box 1)
  - Letter to the editor, 1971 May 22 (Box 1)
    Published in Business Week
  - The Measuring of Monetary Aggregates, undated (Box 1)
  - Methodology of Methodology, undated (Box 1)
  - Misinterpreting a Failure to Disconfirm as Confirmation: A Recurrent Misreading of Significance Tests, undated (Box 1)
  - Monetary Control and the Membership Problem, 1978 (Box 1)
    Statement by Mayer during Hearings before the Committee on Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs
  - Money Stock versus Interest Rates as the Intermediate Target, undated (Box 1)
    Photocopy
  - The Need for a Federal Reserve Commitment, 1981 Jul. 29 (Box 1)
    Photocopy of American Banker
  - On the Usefulness of Economics, 1997 Sept. (Box 1)
    Published by Policy Options Politiques
  - Plant and Equipment Lead Times, 1960 April (Box 1)
  - Policy Simulations with Economic Models, 1989 Dec. (Box 1)
    Published by Methodus
  - Portfolio Regulations and Policies of Financial Intermediaries, 1962 Aug. (Box 1)
    Photocopy of Private Financial Institutions text
  - Proposed discussion forum on Methodologies, undated (Box 1)
    For INEM
  - Reddito e propensione al risparmio, 1967 Oct. (Box 1)
    Published in Mecurio
  - Regulatory Goals for Financial Intermediaries, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Remembering Mark Blaug, 2013 (Box 1)
  - Reply to Questions, 1982 Dec. 30 (Box 1)
    Joint Economic Committee, Congress of the U.S.
  - Risk and Regulation in Banking: Some Proposals for Federal Deposit Insurance Reform, 1971 May (Box 1)
  - Shifting to Indirect Controls (Chinese translation), 1994 Jul. (Box 1)
    Published in Economic Research Center of the State Planning Commission
  - Should Large Banks be Allowed to Fail?, 1975 Nov. (Box 1)
    Reprint
  - The Status of the Monetarist Debate in the US: An Evaluation, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Testimony of Thomas Mayer before the Assembly, 1979 Jun. 6 (Box 1)
    Given to the Finance, Insurance, and Commerce Committee
  - Trade Credits and the Discriminating Effects of Monetary Policy, 1966 Jun. (Box 1)
    National Banking Review reprint
  - Truth versus Precision in Economics, 1993 (Box 1)
    Reviews
  - Using the Constitution to Fight Inflation, 1979 Nov. 29 (Box 1)
    American Banker photocopy
  - Ziliak and McCloskey's Criticism of Significance Tests: As Assessment, 2012 and undated (Box 1)
  - Assorted notes and various theories, undated (Box 1)
  - Binder with photocopied writings, assorted, 1950s-1970s; 4 folders (Box 2)
    Binder (now disbound into 4 folders) assembled by Mayer with reprints, photocopies, and other miscellaneous articles (appendices) written by him or used by him in research.
  - Ethics and Integrity in Economics (AIRLEAP), 2007 and undated (Box 2)
    Correspondence and drafts from Association administration by Mayer
  - Contracts and agreements, 1980s (Box 2)
    Photocopies of Mayer's book contracts; incomplete
- Writings by Others, 1957-2003 and undated; 2
  This series includes articles collected or sent to Mayer, as well as some articles accompanied by his comments and responses. Items are arranged alphabetically by author's name.
  - Comments on "Microfoundational Programs," no author known, undated (Box 1)
  - Review of Larry Boland: "The Foundations of Economic Method: The Hidden Agenda of Mainstream", undated (Box 1)
  - Geoffrey Brennan: "Life in the Putty-Knife Factory", 2003 (Box 1)
  - Bruce Caldwell: "Does Methodology Matter? How Should it be Practiced?", undated (Box 1)
  - Milton Friedman: "How to give Monetarism a Bad Name", 1983 (Box 1)
  - Comments on K. Marwah: "Yet Another Look at Liquidity Trap", undated (Box 1)
  - Interview of Mayer in The Margin, 1988 Mar. 10 (Box 1)
  - Comment on G. Tintner's "An Input-Output Model and Other Economic Studies for Austria," Economic Society Meeting, Philadelphia, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Hans-Michael Trautwein: Thomas Mayer biography, 1994 Apr. 12 (Box 1)
  - John Tukey: "The Philosophy of Multiple Comparisons", undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1971-2014 and undated; 3
  - Correspondence files, 1971-2014 and undated; 6 folders (Box 2)
    Includes letters between Mayer and fellow economists, including Milton Friedman, Roger Backhouse, Tim Congdon, and others. Letters are filed loosely by date.